Bitmap Utilities

Under extra/common/bitmap_utils.fs there is optional code for supporting additional bitmap operations, particularly line and circle-drawing.

Under extra/common/bitmap_lit.fs there is optional code for defining bitmap literals. Bitmap literals specify static blocks of pixels which are used as buffers for instances of bitmap::<bitmap-no-clear> with the same width and height. Note that they are constrained by the maximum line length of 255 bytes that zeptoforth supports.

bitmap-utils

The bitmap-utils module contains the following words:

draw-pixel-line

( constant x0 y0 x1 y1 op dst-bitmap – )

This draws a pixel line with drawing operation op on dst-bitmap from (x0, *y0) to (x1, y1) using the constant value as used by bitmap::draw-pixel-const.

draw-rect-line

( constant width height x0 y0 x1 y1 op dst-bitmap – )

This draws a line with a rectangular pen of width and height with drawing operation op on dst-bitmap from (x0, y0) to (x1, y1) with the pen centered on the line using the constant value as used by bitmap::draw-rect-const. Note that the drawing operation op-xor is not recommended because it will most likely give undesirable results.

draw-bitmap-line

( src-x src-y width height x0 y0 x1 y1 op src-bitmap dst-bitmap – )

This draws a line with the rectangle from (src-x, src-y) to (src-x + width, src-y + height) in src-bitmap as a pen with drawing operation op on dst-bitmap from (x0, y0) to (x1, y1) with the pen centered on the line. Note that the drawing operation op-xor is not recommended because it will most likely give undesirable results. The same may be true of op-set in some cases as well.

draw-pixel-circle

( constant x y radius op dst-bitmap – )

This draws an unfilled pixel circle with drawing operation op on dst-bitmap centered at (x, y) with radius using the constant value as used by *bitmap::draw-pixel-const`.

draw-rect-circle

( constant width height x y radius op dst-bitmap – )

This draws an unfilled circle with a rectangular pen of width and height with drawing operation op on dst-bitmap centered at (x, y) with radius with the pen centered on the edge of the circle using the constant value as used by bitmap::draw-rect-const. Note that the drawing operation op-xor is not recommended because it will most likely give undesirable results.

draw-bitmap-circle

( src-x src-y width height x y radius op src-bitmap dst-bitmap – )

This draws an unfilled circle with the rectangle from (src-x, src-y) to (src-x + width, src-y + height) in src-bitmap as a pen with drawing operation op on dst-bitmap centered at (x, y) with radius with the pen centered on the edge of the circle. Note that the drawing operation op-xor is not recommended because it will most likely give undesirable results. The same may be true of op-set in some cases as well.

draw-filled-circle

( constant x y radius op dst-bitmap – )

This draws a filled pixel circle with drawing operation op on dst-bitmap centered at (x, y) with radius using the constant value as used by *bitmap::draw-pixel-const`.

bitmap-lit

The bitmap-lit class contains the following words:

begin-bitmap-lit

( width height “name” – addr width height y line-addr )

Begin the definition of a bitmap literal.

!!

( addr width height y line-addr “pixels” – addr width height y line-addr )

Define a row of a bitmap literal; all characters until the end of the line above $20 are treated as 1 pixels, all characters until the end of the line from $20 and below are treated as 0 pixels, starting after a single character of whitespace after !!. Note that if the full width of the line is not defined the remaining pixels are set to 0.

end-bitmap-lit

( addr width height y line-addr – )

End the definition of a bitmap literal. Any remaining undefined rows are set to 0.

Bitmaps and Displays

Under extra/common/bitmap.fs there is optional code for supporting bitmap operations. Under extra/common/ssd1306.fs there is optional code for supporting I2C SSD1306-based displays, and similarly under extra/common/ch1116.fs there is optional code for supporting I2C CH1116-based displays. The <bitmap> class is defined under the bitmap module in extra/common/bitmap.fs. The <ssd1306> class inherits from the <bitmap> class and is defined under the ssd1306 module in extra/common/ssd1306.fs, and similarly the <ch1116> class inherits from the <bitmap> class and is defined under the ch1116 module in extra/common/ch1116.fs.

Under extra/common/pixmap16.fs there is optional code for supporting 5-bit red, 6-bit green, 5-bit blue 16-bit pixmap operations, and under extra/common/st7735s.fs there is optional code for supporting SPI ST7735S-based displays with 16-bit color. The <pixmap16> class is defined under the pixmap16 module in extra/common/pixmap16.fs. The <st7735s> class inherits from the <pixmap16> class and is defined under the st7735s module in extra/common/st7735s.fs.

Under extra/common/pixmap8.fs there is optional code for supporting 3-bit red, 3-bit green, 2-bit blue 8-bit pixmap operations. Under extra/common/st7735s_8.fs there is optional code for supporting SPI ST7735S-based displays using 8-bit backing buffers. Under extra/rp_common/st7789v_parallel_8.fs there is optional code for supporting parallel ST7789V-based displays using 8-bit backing buffers. Under extra/common/st7789v_spi_8.fs there is optional code for supporting SPI ST7789V-based displays using 8-bit backing buffers. Note that all of these convert the image data to 16-bit color internally on an as-needed basis. The <pixmap8> class is defined under the pixmap8 module in extra/common/pixmap8.fs. The <st7735s-8> class is defined under the st7735s-8 module in extra/common/st7735s_8.fs. The <st7789v-8> class is defined under the st7789v-8 module in extra/common/st7789v_parallel_8.fs. The <st7789v-8-spi> class is defined under the st7789v-8-spi module in extra/common/st7789v_spi_8.fs. All of these classes inherit from the <pixmap8> class.

The <bitmap> class is a general class for bitmaps and supports both drawing (including setting, or-ing, and-ing, bit-clearing, and exclusive or-ing) individual pixels and rectangles to bitmaps and drawing (including setting, or-ing, and-ing, bit-clearing, and exclusive or-ing) image data from one bitmap onto another bitmap. For bitmaps with dirty state information, i.e. <ssd1306> and <ch1116> objects, drawing operations on bitmaps automatically update their dirty state. Note that the user must provide their own backing bitmap buffer for bitmap objects, whose size must be the number of columns in the bitmap times the number of rows divided by eight (as eight bits are in a byte) rounded up to the next full byte.

The <pixmap16> class is a general class for 5-bit red, 6-bit green, 5-bit blue 16-bit pixmaps and supports both drawing individual pixels and rectangles to pixmaps and drawing image data from one pixmap onto another pixmap; these operations also support using bitmaps as masks. For pixmaps with dirty state information, i.e. ` objects, drawing operationgs on pixmaps automatically update their dirty state. Note that the user must provide their own backing bitmap buffer for bitmap objects, whose size must be the number of columns in the pixmap times hte number of rows multiplied by two bytes per pixel.

The <pixmap8> class is a general class for 3-bit red, 3-bit green, 2-bit blue 8-bit pixmaps and supports both drawing individual pixels and rectangles to pixmaps and drawing image data from one pixmap onto another pixmap; these operations also support using bitmaps as masks. For pixmaps with dirty state information, i.e. ` objects, drawing operationgs on pixmaps automatically update their dirty state. Note that the user must provide their own backing bitmap buffer for bitmap objects, whose size must be the number of columns in the pixmap times hte number of rows multiplied by two bytes per pixel.

The <ssd1306> class implements an SSD1306 device interface and the <ch1116> class implements a CH1116 device interface; they support all the drawing operations implemented by the <bitmap> superclass along with maintaining dirty rectangles for optimizing updates. Drawing operations upon <ssd1306> and <ch1116> objects do not immediately update the display; rather the display must be manually updated after drawing to its backing bitmap. This allows the user to carry out multiple drawing operations in sequence before updating the display at once.

The <st7735s> class implements a 16-bit ST7735S device interface and supports all the drawing operations implemented by the <pixmap16> superclass along with maintaining dirty rectangles for optimizing updates. Drawing operations upon <st7735s> objects do not immediately update the display; rather the display must be manually updated after drawing to its backing pixmap. This allows the user to carry out multiple drawing operations in sequence before updating the display at once.

The <st7735s-8> class implements a 16-bit ST7735S device interface with a 3-bit red, 3-bit green, 2-bit blue 8-bit backing buffer and supports all the drawing operations implemented by the <pixmap8> superclass along with maintaining dirty rectangles for optimizing updates. Drawing operations upon <st7735s-8> objects do not immediately update the display; rather the display must be manually updated after drawing to its backing pixmap. This allows the user to carry out multiple drawing operations in sequence before updating the display at once.

The <st7735s-1> class implements a 16-bit ST7735S device interface with fixed 16-bit foreground and background colors with a bitmap backing buffer and supports all the drawing operations implemented by the <bitmap> superclass along with maintaining dirty rectangles for optimizing updates. Drawing operations upon <st7735s-1> objects do not immediately update the display; rather the display must be manually after drawing to its backing bitmap. This allows the user to carry out multiple drawing operations in sequence before updating the display at once.

The <st7789v-8> and <st7789v-8-spi> classes implement 16-bit ST7789V device interfaces, parallel and SPI respectively, with 3-bit red, 3-bit green, 2-bit blue 8-bit backing buffers and support all the drawing operations implemented by the <pixmap8> superclass along with maintaining dirty rectangles for optimizing updates. Drawing operations upon <st7735s-8> and <st7789-v-spi> objects do not immediately update the display; rather the display must be manually updated after drawing to its backing pixmap. This allows the user to carry out multiple drawing operations in sequence before updating the display at once.

bitmap

The bitmap module contains the following words:

op-set

( – operation )

The set bits operation.

op-or

( – operation )

The or bits operation.

op-and

( – operation )

The and bits operation.

op-bic

( – operation )

The clear bits (i.e not-and) operation.

op-xor

( – operation )

The exclusive-or bits operation.

x-invalid-op

( – )

This exception is raised if an invalid drawing operation is specified.

bitmap-buf-size

( columns rows – bytes )

Get the size of a bitmap buffer in bytes for a given number of columsn and rows.

<bitmap>

( – class )

The <bitmap> class is the base class for bitmaps. It can be used directly, e.g. for offscreen bitmaps, or through its subclasses <ssd1306> and <ch1116>.

The <bitmap> class includes the following constructor:

new

( buffer-addr columns rows bitmap – )

This constructor initializes a <bitmap> instance to have columns columns, rows rows, and a bitmap buffer at address buffer-addr. Note that the buffer pointed to by buffer-addr must be of size columns times rows divided by eight rounded up to the next integer. When this is called, the buffer will be zeroed and the entire bitmap will be marked as dirty.

The <bitmap> class includes the following members:

bitmap-cols

( bitmap – addr )

The address of a cell containing the number of columns in a bitmap.

bitmap-rows

( bitmap – addr )

The address of a cell containing the number of rows in a bitmap.

The <bitmap> class includes the following methods:

dim@

( bitmap – columns rows )

Get the number of columns and rows in a bitmap.

clear-bitmap

( bitmap – )

Set an entire bitmap to zero and mark it as dirty.

dirty?

( bitmap – dirty? )

Get whether a bitmap is dirty. Note that if a bitmap does not have support for dirty state tracking this will always return true.

pixel@

( column row bitmap – state )

Get whether a pixel at column and row in bitmap is on or off, returning true or false respectively. If the pixel is outside the bounds of bitmap, false is returned.

draw-pixel-const

( constant dst-column dst-row op dst-bitmap – )

Apply an operation op to a pixel at dst-column and dst-row of dst-bitmap with a constant value consisting of the bit dst-row modulo eight of constant and mark that pixel as dirty.

draw-rect-const

( constant dst-column dst-row column-count row-count op dst-bitmap – )

Apply an operation op to a rectangle at dst-column to dst-column plus column-count minus one and dst-row to dst-row plus row-count minus one of dst-bitmap with a constant value consisting of the bit row modulo eight of constant and mark that rectangle as dirty.

draw-rect

( src-column src-row dst-column dst-row column-count row-count op src-bitmap dst-bitmap – )

Apply an operation op to a rectangle in dst-bitmap at dst-column to dst-column plus column-count minus one and dst-row to dst-row plus row-count minus one of dst-bitmap with the contents of a rectangle in src-bitmap at src-column to src-column plus column-count minus one and src-row to src-row plus row-count minus one.

pixmap16

Thie pixmap16 module contains the following words:

rgb16

( r g b – color )

Constructs a 16-bit color from three 8-bit components.

pixmap16-buf-size

( cols rows – bytes )

Get the size of a pixmap buffer in bytes for a given number of columns and rows.

The <pixmap16> class is the base class for 16-bit pixmaps. It can be used directly, e.g. for offscreen pixmaps, or through its subclass <st7735s>

The <pixmap16> class includes the following constructor:

new

( buffer-addr columns rows pixmap – )

This constructor initializes a <pixmap16> instance to have columns columns, rows rows, and a pixmap buffer at address buffer-addr. Note that the buffer pointed to by buffer-addr must be of size columns times rows times two. When this is called, the buffer will be zeroed out and the entire pixmap will be marked as dirty.

The <pixmap16> class includes the following members:

pixmap-cols

( pixmap – addr )

The address of a cell containing the number of columns in a pixmap.

pixmap-rows

( pixmap – addr )

The address of a cell containing the number of rows in a pixmap.

The <pixmap16> class includes the following methods:

dim@

( pixmap – columns rows )

Get the number of columns and rows in a pixmap.

clear-pixmap

( pixmap – )

Set an entire pixmap to zero and mark it as dirty.

pixel-addr

( column row pixmap – addr )

Get the address of a pixel in a pixmap’s buffer.

dirty-pixel

( column row pixmap – )

Dirty a pixel in a pixmap; note that this is a no-op in <pixmap16>, but may be overridden in subclasses such as <st7735s>.

dirty-area

( start-column end-column start-row end-row pixmap – )

Dirty a rectangle in a pixmap; note that this is a no-op in <pixmap16>, but may be overridden in subclasses such as <st7735s>.

pixel@

( column row pixmap – color )

Get the color of a pixel at column and row in pixmap. If the pixel is outside the bounds of pixmap, 0 is returned.

draw-pixel-const

( color dst-column dst-row dst-pixmap – )

Draw a single pixel of color *color at dst-column and dst-row on dst-pixmap and mark that pixel as dirty.

draw-rect-const

( color dst-column dst-row column-count row-count dst-pixmap – )

Draw a rectangle of color color at dst-column to dst-column plus column-count minus one and dst-row to dst-row plus row-count minus one of dst-pixmap and mark that rectangle as dirty.

draw-rect

( src-column src-row dst-column dst-row column-count row-count src-pixmap dst-pixmap – )

Copy a rectangle of src-column to src-column plus column-count minus one and src-row to src-row plus row-count minus one of src-pixmap to dst-column to dst-column plus column-count minus one and dst-row to dst-row plus row-count minus one of dst-pixmap and mark that rectangle as dirty.

draw-rect-const-mask

( color mask-column mask-row dst-column dst-row column-count row-count mask-bitmap dst-pixmap – )

Draw a rectangle of color where mask-column to mask-column plus column-count minus one and mask-row to mask-row plus row-count minus one of mask-bitmap is set to one to dst-column to dst-column plus column-count minus one and dst-row to dst-row plus row-count minus one of dst-pixmap and mark that rectangle as dirty.

draw-rect-mask

( mask-column mask-row src-column src-row dst-column dst-row column-count row-count mask-bitmap src-pixmap dst-pixmap – )

Copy a rectangle of src-column to src-column plus column-count minus one and src-row to src-row plus row-count minus one where mask-column to mask-column plus column-count minus one and mask-row to mask-row plus row-count minus one of mask-bitmap is set to one to dst-column to dst-column plus column-count minus one and dst-row to dst-row plus row-count minus one of dst-pixmap and mark that rectangle as dirty.

pixmap8

Thie pixmap8 module contains the following words:

rgb8

( r g b – color )

Constructs a 8-bit color from three 8-bit components.

pixmap8-buf-size

( cols rows – bytes )

Get the size of a pixmap buffer in bytes for a given number of columns and rows.

The <pixmap8> class is the base class for 8-bit pixmaps. It can be used directly, e.g. for offscreen pixmaps, or through its subclass <st7735s-8>

The <pixmap8> class includes the following constructor:

new

( buffer-addr columns rows pixmap – )

This constructor initializes a <pixmap8> instance to have columns columns, rows rows, and a pixmap buffer at address buffer-addr. Note that the buffer pointed to by buffer-addr must be of size columns times rows. When this is called, the buffer will be zeroed out and the entire pixmap will be marked as dirty.

The <pixmap8> class includes the following members:

pixmap-cols

( pixmap – addr )

The address of a cell containing the number of columns in a pixmap.

pixmap-rows

( pixmap – addr )

The address of a cell containing the number of rows in a pixmap.

The <pixmap8> class includes the following methods:

dim@

( pixmap – columns rows )

Get the number of columns and rows in a pixmap.

clear-pixmap

( pixmap – )

Set an entire pixmap to zero and mark it as dirty.

pixel-addr

( column row pixmap – addr )

Get the address of a pixel in a pixmap’s buffer.

dirty-pixel

( column row pixmap – )

Dirty a pixel in a pixmap; note that this is a no-op in <pixmap8>, but may be overridden in subclasses such as <st7735s-8>.

dirty-area

( start-column end-column start-row end-row pixmap – )

Dirty a rectangle in a pixmap; note that this is a no-op in <pixmap8>, but may be overridden in subclasses such as <st7735s-8>.

pixel@

( column row pixmap – color )

Get the color of a pixel at column and row in pixmap. If the pixel is outside the bounds of pixmap, 0 is returned.

draw-pixel-const

( color dst-column dst-row dst-pixmap – )

Draw a single pixel of color *color at dst-column and dst-row on dst-pixmap and mark that pixel as dirty.

draw-rect-const

( color dst-column dst-row column-count row-count dst-pixmap – )

Draw a rectangle of color color at dst-column to dst-column plus column-count minus one and dst-row to dst-row plus row-count minus one of dst-pixmap and mark that rectangle as dirty.

draw-rect

( src-column src-row dst-column dst-row column-count row-count src-pixmap dst-pixmap – )

Copy a rectangle of src-column to src-column plus column-count minus one and src-row to src-row plus row-count minus one of src-pixmap to dst-column to dst-column plus column-count minus one and dst-row to dst-row plus row-count minus one of dst-pixmap and mark that rectangle as dirty.

draw-rect-const-mask

( color mask-column mask-row dst-column dst-row column-count row-count mask-bitmap dst-pixmap – )

Draw a rectangle of color where mask-column to mask-column plus column-count minus one and mask-row to mask-row plus row-count minus one of mask-bitmap is set to one to dst-column to dst-column plus column-count minus one and dst-row to dst-row plus row-count minus one of dst-pixmap and mark that rectangle as dirty.

draw-rect-mask

( mask-column mask-row src-column src-row dst-column dst-row column-count row-count mask-bitmap src-pixmap dst-pixmap – )

Copy a rectangle of src-column to src-column plus column-count minus one and src-row to src-row plus row-count minus one where mask-column to mask-column plus column-count minus one and mask-row to mask-row plus row-count minus one of mask-bitmap is set to one to dst-column to dst-column plus column-count minus one and dst-row to dst-row plus row-count minus one of dst-pixmap and mark that rectangle as dirty.

ssd1306

The ssd1306 module contains the following words:

SSD1306_I2C_ADDR

( – i2c-addr )

The default I2C address for SSD1306-based displays, $3C.

<ssd1306>

( – class )

The <ssd1306> class is the class for I2C SSD1306-based displays. It inherits from the <bitmap> class and can be drawn to using the operations defined in that class. It maintains a dirty rectangle, which is updated when the user invokes its update-display method. Note that column zero is on the lefthand side of the display and row zero is on the top of the display.

The <ssd1306> class includes the following constructor:

new

( pin0 pin1 buffer-addr columns rows i2c-addr i2c-device ssd1306 – )

This constructor initializes an I2C SSD1306 display with the SDA and SCK pins specified as GPIO pins pin0 and pin1 (it does not matter which is which), a backing buffer at buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <bitmap> instances), columns columns, rows rows, the I2C address i2c-addr, the I2C device index i2c-device (note that this must match the I2C device index for pins pin0 and pin1), and the <ssd1306> instance being initialized, ssd1306.

The <ssd1306> class includes the following methoda:

update-display

( ssd1306 – )

This updates the SSD1306-based display with the current contents of its dirty rectangle, and then clears its dirty state. This must be called to update the display’s contents after drawing to the display, which otherwise has no effect on the display itself.

display-contrast!

( constrast ssd1306 – )

This sets the contrast of an SSD1306-based display to a value from 0 to 255.

ch1116

The ch1116 module contains the following words:

CH1116_I2C_ADDR

( – i2c-addr )

The default I2C address for CH1116-based displays, $3C.

<ch1116>

( – class )

The <ch1116> class is the class for I2C CH1116-based displays. It inherits from the <bitmap> class and can be drawn to using the operations defined in that class. It maintains a dirty rectangle, which is updated when the user invokes its update-display method. Note that column zero is on the lefthand side of the display and row zero is on the top of the display.

The <ch1116> class includes the following constructor:

new

( pin0 pin1 buffer-addr columns rows i2c-addr i2c-device ch1116 – )

This constructor initializes an I2C CH1116 display with the SDA and SCK pins specified as GPIO pins pin0 and pin1 (it does not matter which is which), a backing buffer at buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <bitmap> instances), columns columns, rows rows, the I2C address i2c-addr, the I2C device index i2c-device (note that this must match the I2C device index for pins pin0 and pin1), and the <ch1116> instance being initialized, ch1116.

The <ch1116> class includes the following methoda:

update-display

( ch1116 – )

This updates the CH1116-based display with the current contents of its dirty rectangle, and then clears its dirty state. This must be called to update the display’s contents after drawing to the display, which otherwise has no effect on the display itself.

display-contrast!

( constrast ch1116 – )

This sets the contrast of an CH1116-based display to a value from 0 to 255.

st7735s

The st7735s module contains the following words:

<st7735s>

( – class )

The <st7735s> class is the class for 5-bit red, 6-bit green, 5-bit blue 16-bit SPI ST7735S-based displays. It inherits from the <pixmap16> class and can be drawn to using the operations defined in that class. It maintains a dirty rectangle, which is updated when the user invokes its update-display method. Note that column zero is on the lefthand side of the display and row zero is on the top of the display.

The <st7735s> class includes the following constructor:

new

( din-pin clk-pin dc-pin cs-pin backlight-pin reset-pin buffer-addr columns rows spi-device st7735s – )

This constructor initializes an SPI ST7735S display at the SPI device spi-device, a backing buffer at buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <pixmap16> instances), columns columns, rows rows, the DIN pin din-pin, the CLK pin clk-pin, the DC pin dc-pin, the chip-select pin cs-pin, the backlight pin backlight-pin, the reset pin reset-pin, and the <st7735s> instance being initialized, st7735s. Note that din-pin and clk-pin must match the SPI device spi-device specified.

The <st7735s> class includes the following method:

update-display

( st7735s – )

This updates the ST7735S-based display with the current contents of its dirty rectangle, and then clears its dirty state. This must be called to update the display’s contents after drawing to the display, which otherwise has no effect on the display itself.

backlight!

( backlight st7735s – )

Set the on/off state of the ST7735S-based display’s backlight.

st7735s-8

The st7735s-8 module contains the following words:

<st7735s-8>

( – class )

The <st7735s-8> class is the class for 16-bit SPI ST7735S-based displays with 3-bit red, 3-bit green, 2-bit blue 8-bit backing buffers. It inherits from the <pixmap8> class and can be drawn to using the operations defined in that class. It maintains a dirty rectangle, which is updated when the user invokes its update-display method. Note that column zero is on the lefthand side of the display and row zero is on the top of the display.

The <st7735s-8> class includes the following constructor:

new

( din-pin clk-pin dc-pin cs-pin backlight-pin reset-pin buffer-addr columns rows spi-device st7735s – )

This constructor initializes an SPI ST7735S display at the SPI device spi-device, a backing buffer at buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <pixmap16> instances), columns columns, rows rows, the DIN pin din-pin, the CLK pin clk-pin, the DC pin dc-pin, the chip-select pin cs-pin, the backlight pin backlight-pin, the reset pin reset-pin, and the <st7735s-8> instance being initialized, st7735s. Note that din-pin and clk-pin must match the SPI device spi-device specified.

The <st7735s-8> class includes the following method:

update-display

( st7735s – )

This updates the ST7735S-based display with the current contents of its dirty rectangle, and then clears its dirty state. This must be called to update the display’s contents after drawing to the display, which otherwise has no effect on the display itself.

backlight!

( backlight st7735s – )

Set the on/off state of the ST7735S-based display’s backlight.

st7735s-1

The st7735s-1 module contains the following words:

rgb16

( r g b – color )

Create a 16-bit color with 5 bits for red, 6 bits for green, and 5 bits for blue from a red/green/blue triplet of values from 0 to 255 each.

<st7735s-1>

( – class )

The <st7735s-1> class is the class for 16-bit SPI ST7735S-based displays with 5-bit red, 6-bit green, 5-bit blue foreground and background colors and bitmap backing buffers. It inherits from the <bitmap> class and can be drawn to using the operations defined in that class. It maintains a dirty rectangle, which is updated when the user invokes its update-display method. Note that column zero is on the lefthand side of the display and row zero is on the top of the display.

The <st7735s-1> class includes the following constructor:

new

( fg-color bg-color din-pin clk-pin dc-pin cs-pin backlight-pin reset-pin buffer-addr columns rows spi-device st7735s – )

This constructor initializes an SPI ST7735S display at the SPI device spi-device, a backing buffer at buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <bitmap> instances), columns columns, rows rows, the DIN pin din-pin, the CLK pin clk-pin, the DC pin dc-pin, the chip-select pin cs-pin, the backlight pin backlight-pin, the reset pin reset-pin, a 16-bit foreground color fg-color, a 16-bit background color bg-color, and the <st7735s> instance being initialized, st7735s. Note that din-pin and clk-pin must match the SPI device spi-device specified.

The <st7735s> class includes the following method:

update-display

( st7735s – )

This updates the ST7735S-based display with the current contents of its dirty rectangle, and then clears its dirty state. This must be called to update the display’s contents after drawing to the display, which otherwise has no effect on the display itself.

backlight!

( backlight st7735s – )

Set the on/off state of the ST7735S-based display’s backlight.

fg-color!

( fg-color st7735s – )

Set the foreground color of the ST7735S-based display and dirty the display.

bg-color!

( bg-color st7735s – )

Set the background color of the ST7735S-based display and dirty the display.

fg-color@

( st7735s – fg-color )

Get the foreground color of the ST7735S-based display.

bg-color@

( st7735s – bg-color )

Get the background color of the ST7735S-based display.

st7789v-8

The st7789v-8 module contains the following words:

<st7789v-8>

( – class )

The <st7789v-8> class is the class for 16-bit parallel ST7789V-based displays with 3-bit red, 3-bit green, 2-bit blue 8-bit backing buffers. It inherits from the <pixmap8> class and can be drawn to using the operations defined in that class. It maintains a dirty rectangle, which is updated when the user invokes its update-display method. Note that column zero is on the lefthand side of the display and row zero is on the top of the display.

The <st7789v-8> class includes the following constructor:

new

( din-base-pin write-clk-pin read-clk-pin dc-pin cs-pin backlight-pin buffer-addr round? columns rows state-machine pio-device st7789v – )

This constructor initializes a parallel ST7789V display at the PIO device pio-device, the PIO state machine state-machine, a backing buffer at buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <pixmap16> instances), columns columns, rows rows, whether the display is round?, the base DIN pin din-base-pin (note that there are 8 DIN pins with parallel ST7789V displays), the write CLK pin write-clk-pin, the read CLK in read-clk-pin, the DC pin dc-pin, the chip-select pin cs-pin, the backlight pin backlight-pin, and the <st7789v-8> instance being initialized, st7789v.

The <st7789v-8> class includes the following method:

update-display

( st7789v – )

This updates the ST7789V-based display with the current contents of its dirty rectangle, and then clears its dirty state. This must be called to update the display’s contents after drawing to the display, which otherwise has no effect on the display itself.

backlight!

( backlight st7789v – )

Set the on/off state of the ST7789V-based display’s backlight.

st7789v-8-spi

The st7789v-8-spi module contains the following words:

<st7789v-8-spi>

( – class )

The <st7789v-8-spi> class is the class for 16-bit SPI ST7789V-based displays with 3-bit red, 3-bit green, 2-bit blue 8-bit backing buffers. It inherits from the <pixmap8> class and can be drawn to using the operations defined in that class. It maintains a dirty rectangle, which is updated when the user invokes its update-display method. Note that column zero is on the lefthand side of the display and row zero is on the top of the display.

The <st7789v-8-spi> class includes the following constructor:

new

( din-pin clk-pin dc-pin cs-pin backlight-pin reset-pin buffer-addr round? columns rows spi-device st7789v – )

This constructor initializes an SPI ST7789V display at the SPI device spi-device, a backing buffer at buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <pixmap16> instances), columns columns, rows rows, whether the display is round?, the DIN pin din-pin, the CLK pin clk-pin, the DC pin dc-pin, the chip-select pin cs-pin, the backlight pin backlight-pin, the reset pin reset-pin, and the <st7789v-8-spi> instance being initialized, st7789v. Note that din-pin and clk-pin must match the SPI device spi-device specified.

The <st7789v-8-spi> class includes the following method:

update-display

( st7789v – )

This updates the ST7789V-based display with the current contents of its dirty rectangle, and then clears its dirty state. This must be called to update the display’s contents after drawing to the display, which otherwise has no effect on the display itself.

backlight!

( backlight st7789v – )

Set the on/off state of the ST7789V-based display’s backlight.

ENC28J60 Words

A driver for the ENC28J60 10Base-T Ethernet chip is included with zeptoforth. This device uses a SPI interface plus an interrupt line. The external API for this device is provided by the <enc28j60-runner> class in the enc28j60-runner module. This class exposes a frame interface as well as a few control words.

enc28j60-runner

The enc28j60-runner module contains the following constant:

default-mac-addr

( – D: default-mac-addr )

This is a token when provided to the <enc28j60-runner> class when instatiated indicates that the default MAC address is to be used. The default MAC address is derived from the Raspberry Pico 64-bit unique ID, with the AA:00:01 OUI.

The enc28j60-runner module contains the following class:

<enc28j60-runner>

The <enc28j60-runner> class has the constructor:

new

( int-pin spi-pin spi-num D: mac-addr – )

This instantiates an <enc28j60-runner> instance with MAC address mac-addr (or the default address if default-mac-addr is supplied), using the SPI interface block number spi-num and GPIO number spi-pin and the next three in sequence. The interrupt signal uses GPIO number int-pin (which does not have to be adjacent to the SPI connections).

The class will use the GPIO interrupt for processor core 1, and the DMA interrupt. Note that currently zeptoforth does not have a mechanism for allowing multiple users of the same interrupt, so applications may not use these interrupts while the ENC28J60 is in use.

The <enc28j60-runner> class has the following methods:

init-enc28j60-runner

( self – ) Initialize the runner class.

run-enc28j60

( self – ) Start the runner task. Once this is done the device starts receiving packets, and is able to process transmit requests.

enc28j60-enable-mac

( D: d-mac-addr self – ) Enable a MAC address. Normally this is done for multicast addresses, though the device also accepts unicast addresses. This uses a hash filter with a 64 entry hash bitmap, so other addresses than the one requested may also match. The application may need to verify the destination MAC address field in received packets to filter out such spurious matches.

enc28j60-set-duplex

( full-duplex self – ) Set half or full duplex mode (true value for full-duplex sets full duplex mode). Note that the ENC28J60 does not implement standard duplex negotiation or advertisement. If connected to a port that expects negotiation, it will appear as a half duplex interface. Some low cost Ethernet switches support only full duplex.

The default setting is full duplex.

LCD1602 Support

There is an optional driver for I2C LCD1602 displays. The LCD1602 is a 2 row by 16 character text LCD display.

Configuring the LCD1602 is in the form of two steps. The first step is configuring the I2C bus, for which a convenience word init-lcd-i2c is provided; if the user manually configures the I2C bus or previously has used it to access another device, the user must manually call lcd-i2c-device! to set the I2C bus to use with the LCD1602 and then activate-lcd-i2c. The second step is initializing the LCD1602 device, which is done through calling init-lcd. These steps must be carried out before using the LCD1602 device.

LCD1602 support is in extra/rp_common/lcd1602.fs, which can be compiled either to RAM or to flash as needed. There is a demo program which uses it in extra/rp_common/lcd1602_demo.fs.

lcd1602

The lcd1602 module contains the following words:

init-lcd-i2c

( pin1 pin2 i2c-device – )

Configure the I2C bus i2c-device to use GPIO’s pin1 and pin2 and set it up to communicate with the LCD1602 device on that bus.

init-lcd

( – )

Initialize the LCD1602 device. The I2C bus must be set up to communicate with the LCD1602 device first.

lcd-i2c-device!

( i2c-device – )

Manually set the I2C bus i2c-device to use with the LCD1602 without initializing the I2C bus itself.

activate-lcd-i2c

( – )

Manually set the I2C bus configured with init-lcd-i2c or lcd-i2c-device! to communicate with the LCD1602 device. This is necessary if the I2C bus has been configured manually or if another device has been previously used on the I2C bus.

clear-display

( – )

Clear the LCD1602 display.

put-text

( row col c-addr bytes – )

Write the specified string to the LCD1602 display at the specified row and column.

Neopixels on the RP2040 and RP2350

There is optional support for Neopixels and Neopixel strips on the RP2040 and RP2350 using a PIO block to drive the Neopixel protocol.

Configuring the Neopixel is as simple as alloting a Neopixel data structure for a given number of Neopixels and initializing it with a Neopixel data GPIO pin, a Neopixel count, a PIO state machine index, and a PIO. Once one has done that, neopixel! can be used to specify the colors of individual Neopixels (with RGB colors, with each element having values from 0 to 255), and once the colors have been specified one transmits them to the Neopixel strip with update-neopixel.

Note that in some setups, such as the SeeedStudio XIAO RP2040, a separate GPIO pin may need to be set high to enable a Neopixel (e.g. GPIO pin 11 on the SeeedStudio XIAO RP2040, in addition to the data GPIO pin 12). Use the pin! word in the pin module for this.

Neopixel support is in extra/rp_common/neopixel.fs, which can be compiled either to RAM or to flash as needed.

neopixel

The neopixel module contains the following words:

init-neopixel

( state-machine pio count pin addr – )

Initialize a Neopixel structure at addr for count Neopixels, data GPIO pin pin, PIO block pio, and state machine state-machine. This does not take into account any power GPIO pin that may need to be configured. It reprograms the specified PIO block and assumes that it has full control over said block. Note that if sm and pio are both -1, they will be automatically assigned via the PIO pool; otherwise sm must be from 0 to 3 and pio must be one of pio::PIO0, pio::PIO1, or, on the RP2350, pio::PIO2.

clear-neopixel

( neopixel – )

Clear all the Neopixel states in Neopixel structure neopixel.

update-neopixel

( neopixel – )

Transmit all the stored Neopixel color data for the Neopixels in Neopixel structure neopixel.

neopixel!

( red green blue index neopixel – )

Specify the color of Neopixel index in the Neopixel structure neopixel as red, green, and blue color components from 0 to 255. Note that this does not transmit the color data to the Neopixel in question; rather one must call update-neopixel to do so.

neopixel@

( index neopixel – red green blue )

Get the color of Neopixel index in the Neopixel structure neopixel as red, green, and blue color components from 0 to 255.

neopixel-size

( count – bytes )

Get the size of a Neopixel structure in bytes with count Neopixels.

x-out-of-range-neopixel

( – )

Out of range Neopixel index exception.

x-out-of-range-color

( – )

Out of range color component exception.

zeptoIP Words

zeptoIP is an Internet Protocol stack for zeptoforth. Currently it supports the Raspberry Pi Pico W and Raspberry Pi Pico 2 W’s CYW43439 WiFi chip. Unofficially it should also work on the Pimoroni Pico Plus 2 W as well. By design it can be extended to any WiFi or Ethernet interface which exposes receiving and sending Ethernet frames. It expressly does not support WiFi interfaces such as the ESP8285 on the Wio RP2040 which operate by using their own protocols such as the “AT” protocol. Note that there are separate bodies of code for zeptoIP for IPv4 and IPv6, which are referred to in particular as zeptoIPv4 and zeptoIPv6.

zeptoIP is centered around one or more interfaces, instances of net::<interface>each of which has its own IPv4 or IPv6 address (and in the case of IPv6 there is also a link-local IPv6 address), netmask in the case of IPv4, prefix and prefix length in the case of IPv6, gateway IPv4 or IPv6 address, and DNS server IPv4 or IPv6 address. With interfaces sources of incoming (and in the case of TCP data, outgoing) data, known as endpoints, instances of net::<endpoint> may be created, endpoints with ready data or state changes can be fetched, UDP packets may be sent, IP addresses of hostnames can be resolved via DNS, and IPv4 and IPv6 addresses may be acquired via DHCP or, in the case of IPv6, SLAAC.

Endpoints encapsulate connection state in the case of TCP, and received packet state in the case of UDP. Reading received data from an endpoint need not require copying the data; the received data associated with an endpoint is valid until the endpoint is marked as done, at which the received data is cleared from the endpoint’s buffer and the room it took up in the endpoint’s buffer is made available for more received data. Note that data continues to be received even between the time that ready endpoint is fetched with net::get-ready-endpoint or is waited for with net::wait-ready-endpoint and it is marked as done with net::endpoint-done. Also note that with UDP endpoints the ready data at any one data comprises only a single received UDP packet’s data.

The typical means by which endpoints are serviced is by creating an endpoint processor, an instance of endpoint-process::<endpoint-process>, and registering an endpoint handler, an instance of endpoint-process::<endpoint-handler> with it. The endpoint processor involves a task which fetches ready endpoints one at a time from an interface, and then applies it to each registered endpoint handler. Once all the endpoint handlers have processed the endpoint, it should be marked as done to make it available for new data or state changes.

A more conventional approach to servicing endpoints, albeit one that requires multiple tasks if multiple endpoints are to be serviced, is through calling net::wait-ready-endpoint, which blocks until the endpoint is ready, and then promotes the data its receive buffer.

Sending data is done differently with regard to TCP and UDP. With TCP sending data requires a TCP endpoint, gotten through either receiving an incoming connection on a listening TCP endpoint, started with net::allocate-tcp-listen-endpoint, which will result in the endpoint being readied with the appropriate state change(s), or starting a TCP connection with net-ipv4::allocate-tcp-connect-ipv4-endpoint (for IPv4) or net-ipv6::allocate-tcp-connect-ipv6-endpoint (for IPv6), at which an TCP endpoint will be provided to the user. Once one has done this, all that one must do is call send-tcp-endpoint, which will send the provided data unless the connection is closed or reset, where then it will exit prematurely. With UDP sending data simply requires executing net-ipv4::send-ipv4-udp-packet (for IPv4) or net-ipv6::send-ipv6-udp-packet (for IPv6).

Closing an endpoint is accomplished through net::close-tcp-endpoint, for TCP endpoints, and net::close-udp-endpoint, for UDP endpoints. Closing UDP endpoints is immediate, while closing TCP endpoints involves waiting for the endpoint to be closed after a four-way handshake.

If the user wishes to listen to multiple connections on the same point they must allocate multiple endpoints to listen on; incoming connections will be alloted to each of these endpoints.

Note that there is a fixed number of available endpoints which is set at compile-time, specified by the constant net-config::max-endpoints. This is set to four by default.

net

The net module contains the following words:

x-oversized-frame

( – )

This exception is raised if a frame larger than the MTU would be raised.

x-invalid-dns-name

( – )

This exception is raised if an invalid DNS name is provided.

The net module contains the following classes:

<interface>

The <interface> class has the following methods:

intf-mac-addr@

( interface – D: mac-addr )

Get an interface’s MAC address.

send-tcp-endpoint

( addr bytes endpoint interface – )

Send bytes at addr to the peer of endpoint. This will return when sending data is complete or if the connection is closed or its connection is not yet established.

evict-dns

( c-addr bytes interface – )

Evict a DNS name’s cache entry, forcing it to be re-resolved.

get-ready-endpoint

( interface – endpoint )

Do a blocking wait to get the next ready endpoint; note that the user may use task::timeout to apply a timeout to this.

wait-ready-endpoint

( endpoint interface – )

Do a blocking wait until the given endpoint becomes ready; note that the user may use task::timeout to apply a timeout to this.

endpoint-done

( endpoint interface – )

Retire the current pending data for an endpoint and allow the endpoint to be readied again; if there is data already available, the endpoint will be readied again immediately.

allocate-udp-listen-endpoint

( port interface – endpoint success? )

Attempt to allocate a UDP endpoint listening on port (which may be any port from net-consts::MIN_EPHEMERAL_PORT to net-consts::MAX_EPHEMERAL_PORT if net-consts::EPHEMERAL_PORT is provided) and return true along with the endpoint, unless no endpoints are free, where then false is returned along with a padding cell.

allocate-tcp-listen-endpoint

( port interface – endpoint success? )

Attempt to allocate a TCP endpoint listening on port (which may be any port from net-consts::MIN_EPHEMERAL_PORT to net-consts::MAX_EPHEMERAL_PORT if net-consts::EPHEMERAL_PORT is provided) and return true along with the endpoint, unless no endpoints are free, where then false is returned along with a padding cell.

close-udp-endpoint

( endpoint interface – )

Close a UDP endpoint. This is immediate, and any queued UDP packets will be lost.

close-tcp-endpoint

( endpoint interface – )

Close a TCP endpoint. This waits until the connection is normally closed or the connection is reset.

<endpoint>

The <endpoint> class has the following methods:

endpoint-tcp-state@

( endpoint – tcp-state )

This word returns the current TCP state of an endpoint.

endpoint-rx-data@

( endpoint – addr bytes )

This word returns the address and size in bytes of the current pending data for an endpoint.

udp-endpoint?

( endpoint – udp? )

Get whether an endpoint is a UDP endpoint; note that if this returns false it means the endpoint is a TCP endpoint (by default endpoints are TCP endpoints).

endpoint-local-port@

( endpoint – port )

Get the local port for endpoint. Note that if the local port for an endpoint had been specified as net-consts::EPHEMERAL_PORT this will be the actual local port.

waiting-rx-data?

( endpoint – waiting? )

Get whether there is any data waiting on endpoint beyond the currently pending data.

net-ipv4

The net-ipv4 module contains the following classes:

<ipv4-interface>

The <ipv4-interface> class inherits from net::<interface> and has the following constructor:

new

( frame-interface interface – )

This constructs an <ipv4-interface> instance for a given frame interface, an instance of frame-interface::<frame-interface>, which encapsulates a connection to the hardware network interface.

The <ipv4-interface> class has the following methods:

intf-ipv4-addr@

( interface – addr )

Get an interface’s IPv4 address.

intf-ipv4-addr!

( addr interface – )

Manually set an interface’s IPv4 address.

intf-ipv4-netmask@

( interface – netmask )

Get an interface’s IPv4 netmask.

intf-ipv4-netmask!

( netmask interface – )

Manually set an interface’s IPv4 netmask.

gateway-ipv4-addr@

( interface – addr )

Get an interface’s gateway’s IPv4 address.

gateway-ipv4-addr!

( addr interface – )

Manually set an interface’s gateway’s IPv4 address.

dns-server-ipv4-addr@

( interface – addr )

Get an interface’s DNS server’s IPv4 address.

dns-server-ipv4-addr!

( addr interface – )

Manually set an interface’s gateway’s IPv4 address.

intf-ipv4-broadcast@

( interface – addr )

Get an interface’s IPv4 broadcast address.

intf-ttl@

( interface – tll )

Get an interface’s TTL.

intf-ttl!

( ttl interface – )

Set an interface’s TTL.

discover-ipv4-addr

( interface – )

Discover an interface’s IPv4 address, IPv4 netmask, gateway IPv4 address, and DNS server IPv4 address via DHCP.

send-ipv4-udp-packet

( ? src-port dest-addr dest-port bytes xt interface – ? success? )

This will call xt with a signature of ( ? buffer – ? send? ) with an address of a buffer guaranteed to be of size bytes to construct a UDP packet with a payload consisting of that buffer from src-port (which may be any port from net-consts::MIN_EPHEMERAL_PORT to net-consts::MAX_EPHEMERAL_PORT if net-consts::EPHEMERAL_PORT is provided) to dest-addr at dest-port; if true is returned the packet is sent, and true will be returned afterwards, else the packet is not sent and false is returned. Note that false may be returned if the MAC address corresponding to dest-addr cannot be resolved.

resolve-ipv4-addr-mac-addr

( dest-addr interface – D: mac-addr success? )

Attempt to resolve the MAC address of an IPv4 address; if successful, true and the MAC address are returned, else false and padding cells are returned.

resolve-dns-ipv4-addr

( c-addr bytes interface – ipv4-addr success? )

Attempt to resolve the IPv4 address of a hostname via DNS; if successful, true and the IPv4 address are returned, else false and a apdding cell is returned.

allocate-tcp-connect-ipv4-endpoint

( src-port dest-addr dest-port interface – endpoint success? )

Attempt to allocate a TCP endpoint connected to the IPv4 address dest-addr at dest-port from src-port (which may be any port from net-consts::MIN_EPHEMERAL_PORT to net-consts::MAX_EPHEMERAL_PORT if net-consts::EPHEMERAL_PORT is provided) and return true along with the endpoint, unless no endpoints are free, wheree then false is returned along with a padding cell.

<ipv4-endpoint>

The <ipv4-endpoint> class inherits from net::<endpoint> and has the following method:

endpoint-ipv4-remote@

( endpoint – ipv4-addr port )

This word returns the IPv4 address and port of, for a TCP endpoint, the peer of a connection, and for a UDP endpoint, the packet for the current pending data.

<ipv4-handler>

The <ipv4-handler> class handles receiving IPv4 frames from a frame interface and passing them on to an instance of <ipv4-interface>.

The <ipv4-handler> class has the following constructor:

new

( interface handler – )

Construct an IPv4 frame handler for interface.

The <ipv4-handler> class has the following methods:

handle-frame

( addr bytes handler – )

Handle a received frame.

handle-refresh

( handler – )

Handle periodic housekeeping activities.

<arp-handler>

The <arp-handler> class handles receiving ARP frames from a frame interface and passing them onto an instance of <interface>.

The <arp-handler> class has the following constructor:

new

( interface handler – )

Construct an ARP frame handler for interface.

The <arp-handler> class has the following methods:

handle-frame

( addr bytes handler – )

Handle a received frame.

handle-refresh

( handler – )

Handle periodic housekeeping activities.

net-ipv6

The net-ipv6 module contains the following classes:

<ipv6-interface>

The <ipv6-interface> class inherits from net::<interface> and has the following constructor:

new

( frame-interface interface – )

This constructs an <ipv6-interface> instance for a given frame interface, an instance of frame-interface::<frame-interface>, which encapsulates a connection to the hardware network interface.

The <ipv6-interface> class has the following methods:

intf-ipv6-addr@

( interface – addr-0 addr-1 addr-2 addr-3 )

Get an interface’s primary IPv6 address.

intf-ipv6-addr!

( addr-0 addr-1 addr-2 addr-3 interface – )

Manually set an interface’s primary IPv6 address.

intf-link-local-ipv6-addr@

( interface – addr-0 addr-1 addr-2 addr-3 )

Get an interface’s link-local IPv6 address.

intf-link-local-ipv6-addr!

( addr-0 addr-1 addr-2 addr-3 interface – )

Manually set an interface’s link-local IPv6 address.

intf-slaac-ipv6-addr@

( interface – addr-0 addr-1 addr-2 addr-3 )

Get an interface’s SLAAC IPv6 address.

intf-slaac-ipv6-addr!

( addr-0 addr-1 addr-2 addr-3 interface – )

Manually set an interface’s SLAAC IPv6 address.

intf-dhcpv6-ipv6-addr@

( interface – addr-0 addr-1 addr-2 addr-3 )

Get an interface’s DHCPv6 IPv6 address.

intf-dhcpv6-ipv6-addr!

( addr-0 addr-1 addr-2 addr-3 interface – )

Manually set an interface’s DHCPv6 IPv6 address.

intf-ipv6-prefix@

( interface – prefix-0 prefix-1 prefix-2 prefix-3 )

Get an interface’s prefix

intf-ipv6-prefix!

( prefix-0 prefix-1 prefix-2 prefix-3 interface – )

Manually set an interface’s prefix

intf-ipv6-prefix-len@

( interface – bits )

Get the length of an interface’s prefix in bits.

intf-ipv6-prefix-len!

( bits interface – )

Manually set the length of an interface’s prefix in bits.

intf-autonomous@

( interface – autonomous? )

Get whether an interface is autonomous (note that this does not mean that it does not use DHCPv6).

intf-autonomous!

( autonomous? interface – )

Manually set whether an interface is autonomous.

gateway-ipv6-addr@

( interface – addr )

Get an interface’s gateway’s IPv6 address.

gateway-ipv6-addr!

( addr interface – )

Manually set an interface’s gateway’s IPv6 address.

dns-server-ipv6-addr@

( interface – addr )

Get an interface’s DNS server’s IPv6 address.

dns-server-ipv6-addr!

( addr interface – )

Manually set an interface’s gateway’s IPv6 address.

intf-hop-limit@

( interface – hop-limit )

Get an interface’s hop limit.

intf-hop-limit!

( hop-limit interface – )

Manually set an interface’s hop limit.

init-multicast

( interface – )

Initialize the link-local Ethernet multicast address used by IPv6. Note that this is automatically called when simple-net-ipv6::<simple-net-ipv6> is initialized.

autoconfigure-link-local-ipv6-addr

( interface – success? )

Autoconfigure a link local IPv6 address. It is recommended that one do this first when bringing up an IPv6 interface. Returns false if an address collision is detected, otherwise true.

discover-ipv6-router

( interface – )

Discover an IPv6 router using neighbor discovery. It is recommended that one do this after autoconfiguring the link local IPv6 address except on setups where there is no router.

discover-ipv6-addr

( interface – success? )

Discover an IPv6 address using SLAAC and/or DHCPv6. This requires that an IPv6 router has been discovered first. Returns false if an address collision is detected, otherwise true.

discover-dns-ipv6-addr

( interface – )

Discover a DNS server IPv6 address. This requires that an IPv6 router has been discovered first.

send-ipv6-udp-packet

( ? src-port dest-addr-0 dest-addr-1 dest-addr-2 dest-addr-3 dest-port bytes xt interface – ? success? )

This will call xt with a signature of ( ? buffer – ? send? ) with an address of a buffer guaranteed to be of size bytes to construct a UDP packet with a payload consisting of that buffer from src-port (which may be any port from net-consts::MIN_EPHEMERAL_PORT to net-consts::MAX_EPHEMERAL_PORT if net-consts::EPHEMERAL_PORT is provided) to (dest-addr-0, dest-addr-1, dest-addr-2, dest-addr-3) at dest-port; if true is returned the packet is sent, and true will be returned afterwards, else the packet is not sent and false is returned. Note that false may be returned if the MAC address corresponding to (dest-addr-0, dest-addr-1, dest-addr-2, dest-addr-3) cannot be resolved.

resolve-ipv6-addr-mac-addr

( dest-addr interface – D: mac-addr success? )

Attempt to resolve the MAC address of an IPv6 address; if successful, true and the MAC address are returned, else false and padding cells are returned.

resolve-dns-ipv6-addr

( c-addr bytes interface – addr-0 addr-1 addr-2 addr-3 success? )

Attempt to resolve the IPv6 address of a hostname, i.e. the first AAAA record, via DNS; if successful, true and the IPv6 address are returned, else false and a apdding cell is returned.

allocate-tcp-connect-ipv6-endpoint

( src-port dest-addr-0 dest-addr-1 dest-addr-2 dest-addr-3 dest-port interface – endpoint success? )

Attempt to allocate a TCP endpoint connected to the IPv6 address (dest-addr-0, dest-addr-1, dest-addr-2, dest-addr-3) at dest-port from src-port (which may be any port from net-consts::MIN_EPHEMERAL_PORT to net-consts::MAX_EPHEMERAL_PORT if net-consts::EPHEMERAL_PORT is provided) and return true along with the endpoint, unless no endpoints are free, wheree then false is returned along with a padding cell.

<ipv6-endpoint>

The <ipv6-endpoint> class inherits from net::<endpoint> and has the following method:

endpoint-ipv6-remote@

( endpoint – ipv6-addr-0 ipv6-addr-1 ipv6-addr-2 ipv6-addr-3 port )

This word returns the IPv6 address and port of, for a TCP endpoint, the peer of a connection, and for a UDP endpoint, the packet for the current pending data.

<ipv6-handler>

The <ipv6-handler> class handles receiving IPv6 frames from a frame interface and passing them on to an instance of <ipv6-interface>.

The <ipv6-handler> class has the following constructor:

new

( interface handler – )

Construct an IPv6 frame handler for interface.

The <ipv6-handler> class has the following methods:

handle-frame

( addr bytes handler – )

Handle a received frame.

handle-refresh

( handler – )

Handle periodic housekeeping activities.

net-consts

The net-consts module contains the following words:

TCP states

There are the following TCP states:

TCP_CLOSED

TCP_LISTEN

TCP_SYN_SENT

TCP_SYN_RECEIVED

TCP_ESTABLISHED

TCP_FIN_WAIT_1

TCP_FIN_WAIT_2

TCP_CLOSING

TCP_CLOSE_WAIT

TCP_LAST_ACK

TCP_TIME_WAIT

Ports

MIN_EPHEMERAL_PORT

The minimum ephemeral port, 49152.

MAX_EPHEMERAL_PORT

The maximum ephemeral port, 65534 (port 65535 is use by zeptoIP for DNS).

EPHEMERAL_PORT

A token indicating that for a source port an ephemeral port is to be used. Ephemeral ports are chosen by choosing a random port between MIN_EPHEMERAL_PORT and MAX_EPHEMERAL_PORT, inclusive, on initialization, and then incrementing the ephemeral port each time an ephemeral port is needed, wrapping around within this range.

endpoint-process

The endpoint-process module contains the following classes:

<endpoint-handler>

The <endpoint-handler> class is meant to be subclassed by the user, who shall provide an implementation of the handle-endpoint method.

The <endpoint-handler> class contains the following methods:

handle-endpoint

( endpoint process – )

Handle a ready endpoint; note that endpoint should be marked as done before it is available for furthe processing. The user shall provide their own implementation of this method.

handle-timeout

( process – )

Handle a timeout, based on the timeout returned by handler-timeout@.

handler-timeout@

( process – timeout )

Get the current timeout for an endpoint handler in ticks from the present; note that task::no-timeout signifies there being no timeout.

<endpoint-process>

The <endpoint-process> class encapsulates a task carrying out the core loop of handling input and state changes on endpoints associated with a interface.

The <endpoint-process> class has the following constructor:

new

( interface process – )

This constructor sets the interface for the endpoint processor to interface.

The <endpoint-process> class has the following methods:

add-endpoint-handler

( handler process – )

Add a endpoint handler.

run-endpoint-process

( process – )

This starts the task for processing endpoints on the chosen interface.

endpoint-process-priority!

( priority self – )

Set the endpoint processor priority. The default endpoint processor priority is 0. This method can be called before run-endpoint-process to set the priority of the endpoint processor when it is started.

endpoint-process-priority@

( self – priority )

Get the endpoint processor priority. The default endpoint processor priority is 0.

endpoint-process-interval!

( interval self – )

Set the endpoint processor interval in ticks, which are normally 100 us increments. A negative interval means that the endpoint processor operates as a normal task, and -1 is the default value. This method can be called before run-endpoint-process to set the interval of the endpoint processor when it is started with.

endpoint-process-interval@

( self – interval )

Get the endpoint processor interval in ticks, which are normally 100 us increments. A negative interval means that the endpoint processor operates as a normal task, and -1 is the default value.

endpoint-process-deadline!

( deadline self – )

Set the endpoint processor deadline in ticks, which are normally 100 us increments, with the current time in ticks being systick::systick-counter. Note that this raises x-endpoint-process-not-started if called before run-endpoint-process has been called.

endpoint-process-deadline@

( self – deadline )

Get the endpoint processor deadline in ticks, which are normally 100 us increments, with the current time in ticks being systick::systick-counter. Note that this raises x-endpoint-process-not-started if called before run-endpoint-process has been called.

frame-process

The frame-process module contains the following classes:

<frame-handler>

The <frame-handler> class is meant to be subclassed by the user, who shall provide an implementation of the handle-frame and handle-refresh methods.

The <frame-handler> class contains the following method:

handle-frame

( addr bytes process – )

Handle a frame of bytes at addr.

handle-refresh

( process – )

Carry out periodic housekeeeping activities.

<frame-process>

The <frame-process> class encapsulates receiving frames from a frame interface and handling periodic housekeeping activties.

The <frame-process> class has the following constructor:

new

( frame-interface process – )

This constructor sets the frame interface for the frame processor to frame-interface.

The <frame-process> class has the following methods:

add-frame-handler

( handler process – )

Add a frame handler.

run-frame-process

( process – )

This starts the task for processing frames and doing periodic housekeeping on the chosen frame interface.

frame-interface

The frame-interface module encapsulates the interface between a network and zeptoIP, by providing a means of receiving and sending frames.

The frame-interface module contains the following class:

<frame-interface>

The <frame-interface> class is meant to be subclassed by implementors of interfaces to external networks.

The <frame-interface> class contains the following abstract methods:

mtu-size@

( frame-interface – bytes )

Get the MTU size.

mac-addr@

( frame-interface – D: mac-addr )

Get the MAC address.

mac-addr!

( D: mac-addr frame-interface – )

Set the MAC address.

add-multicast-filter

( D: mac-addr frame-interface – )

Add a MAC address to a multicast filter if there is a multicast filter; if there is no multicast filter this is a no-op. Note that if a MAC address is already in a multicast filter this is a no-op. There may be an implementation-dependent limit on the number of entries in a multicast filter.

remove-multicast-filter

( D: mac-addr frame-interface – )

Remove a MAC address from a multicast filter if there is a multicast filter; if there is no multicast filter this is a no-op. Note that if a MAC address is not in a multicast filter this is a no-op.

put-rx-frame

( addr bytes frame-interface – )

Put a received frame.

get-rx-frame

( addr bytes frame-interface – bytes’ )

Get a received frame.

poll-rx-frame

( addr bytes frame-interface – bytes’ found? )

Poll a received frame.

put-tx-frame

( addr bytes frame-interface – )

Put a frame to transmit.

get-tx-frame

( addr bytes frame-interface – bytes’ )

Get a frame to transmit.

poll-tx-frame

( addr bytes frame-interface – bytes’ found? )

Poll a frame to transmit.

simple-net-ipv4

The simple-net-ipv4 module contains the following word:

x-endpoint-process-not-started

( – )

This exception is raised if one attempts to obtain the endpoint process from a <simple-net-ipv4> instance for which the endpoint process has not been started.

The simple-net-ipv4 module contains the following class:

<simple-net-ipv4>

The <simple-net-ipv4> class is a base class for encapsulating a network interface driver and a zeptoIPv4 network stack while simplifying their configuration.

It has the following constructor:

new

( driver – )

This is a basic constructor that initializes the state of the <simple-net-ipv4> base class.

It has the following methods:

init-net

( driver – )

This initializes a <simple-net-ipv4> instance.

init-net-no-handler

( driver – )

This initalizes a <simple-net-ipv4> instance without starting an endpoint processing task.

device-frame-interface@

( driver – frame-interface )

This gets the network interface driver’s frame interface instance.

net-interface@

( driver – interface )

This gets the zeptoIPv4 interface instance.

net-frame-process@

( driver – frame-processor )

This gets the zeptoIP frame processor instance.

net-endpoint-process@

( driver – endpoint-processor )

This gets the zeptoIP endpoint processor instance. This raises x-endpoint-process-not-started if init-net has not been called (e.g. if init-net-no-handler has been called instead).

run-net-process

( driver – )

This starts the zeptoIP frame and endpoint processors.

The simple-net-ipv6 module contains the following class:

<simple-net-ipv6>

The <simple-net-ipv6> class is a base class for encapsulating a network interface driver and a zeptoIPv6 network stack while simplifying their configuration.

It has the following constructor:

new

( driver – )

This is a basic constructor that initializes the state of the <simple-net-ipv6> base class.

It has the following methods:

init-net

( driver – )

This initializes a <simple-net-ipv6> instance.

init-net-no-handler

( driver – )

This initalizes a <simple-net-ipv6> instance without starting an endpoint processing task.

device-frame-interface@

( driver – frame-interface )

This gets the network interface driver’s frame interface instance.

net-interface@

( driver – interface )

This gets the zeptoIPv6 interface instance.

net-frame-process@

( driver – frame-processor )

This gets the zeptoIP frame processor instance.

net-endpoint-process@

( driver – endpoint-processor )

This gets the zeptoIP endpoint processor instance. This raises x-endpoint-process-not-started if init-net has not been called (e.g. if init-net-no-handler has been called instead).

run-net-process

( driver – )

This starts the zeptoIP frame and endpoint processors.

simple-cyw43-net-ipv4

The simple-cyw43-net-ipv4 module contains the following class:

<simple-cyw43-net-ipv4>

The <simple-cyw43-net-ipv4> class encapsulates a CYW43xxx driver and a zeptoIPv4 network stack while simplifying their configuration.

It has the following constructor:

new

( pwr-pin dio-pin cs-pin clk-pin sm-index pio-instance driver – )

This instantiates an instance with pwr-pin, dio-pin, cs-pin, and pio-pin being specified as the GPIO pins for communication with the CYW43xxx, and a PIO state machine sm-index, and a PIO instance (pio::PIO0 or pio::PIO1 or, on the RP2350, pio::PIO2) for the PIO program and state machine for implementing the half-duplex protocol for communicating with the CYW43xxx.

It has the following methods:

init-cyw43-net

( driver – )

This method is an alias for simple-net-ipv4::init-net.

init-cyw43-net-no-handler

( driver – )

This method is an alias for simple-net-ipv4::init-net-no-handler.

cyw43-net-country!

( abbrev-addr abbrev-bytes code-addr code-bytes country-rev self – )

Initialize the country abbrevation, code, and revision; these default to XX, XX, and -1. Note that this must be called before init-cyw43-net, if it called at all.

cyw43-gpio!

( state gpio driver – )

This sets a GPIO pin on the CYW43xxx.

cyw43-control@

( driver – control )

This gets the CYW43xxx controller instance.

net-interface@

( driver – interface )

This method is an alias for simple-net-ipv4::net-interface@.

net-endpoint-process@

( driver – endpoint-processor )

This method is an alias for simple-net-ipv4::net-endpoint-process@.

run-net-process

( driver – )

This method is an alias for simple-net-ipv4::run-net-process.

simple-cyw43-net-ipv6

The simple-cyw43-net-ipv6 module contains the following class:

<simple-cyw43-net-ipv6>

The <simple-cyw43-net-ipv6> class encapsulates a CYW43xxx driver and a zeptoIPv6 network stack while simplifying their configuration.

It has the following constructor:

new

( pwr-pin dio-pin cs-pin clk-pin sm-index pio-instance driver – )

This instantiates an instance with pwr-pin, dio-pin, cs-pin, and pio-pin being specified as the GPIO pins for communication with the CYW43xxx, and a PIO state machine sm-index, and a PIO instance (pio::PIO0 or pio::PIO1 or, on the RP2350, pio::PIO2) for the PIO program and state machine for implementing the half-duplex protocol for communicating with the CYW43xxx.

It has the following methods:

init-cyw43-net

( driver – )

This method is an alias for simple-net-ipv6::init-net.

init-cyw43-net-no-handler

( driver – )

This method is an alias for simple-net-ipv6::init-net-no-handler.

cyw43-net-country!

( abbrev-addr abbrev-bytes code-addr code-bytes country-rev self – )

Initialize the country abbrevation, code, and revision; these default to XX, XX, and -1. Note that this must be called before init-cyw43-net, if it called at all.

cyw43-gpio!

( state gpio driver – )

This sets a GPIO pin on the CYW43xxx.

cyw43-control@

( driver – control )

This gets the CYW43xxx controller instance.

net-interface@

( driver – interface )

This method is an alias for simple-net-ipv6::net-interface@.

net-endpoint-process@

( driver – endpoint-processor )

This method is an alias for simple-net-ipv6::net-endpoint-process@.

run-net-process

( driver – )

This method is an alias for simple-net-ipv6::run-net-process.

pico-w-cyw43-net-ipv4

This pico-w-cyw43-net-ipv4 class has the following class:

<pico-w-cyw43-net-ipv4>

The <pico-w-cyw43-net-ipv4> class inherits from the <simple-cyw43-net-ipv4> class, providing functionality specific to the Raspberry Pi Pico W.

It has the following constructor:

new

( sm-index pio-instance driver – )

This instantiates an instance with a PIO state machine sm-index, and a PIO instance (pio::PIO0 or pio::PIO1 or, on the RP2350, pio::PIO2) for the PIO program and state machine for implementing the half-duplex protocol for communicating with the CYW43xxx.

It has the following methods:

init-cyw43-net

( driver – )

This initializes a <pico-w-cyw43-net-ipv4> instance.

init-cyw43-net-no-handler

( driver – )

This initalizes a <pico-w-cyw43-net-ipv4> instance without starting an endpoint processing task.

pico-w-led!

( state driver – )

This sets the LED on the Raspberry Pi Pico W or Raspberry Pi Pico 2 W to state.

pico-w-led@

( driver – state )

This gets the state of the LED on the Raspberry Pi Pico W or Raspberry Pi Pico 2 W.

toggle-pico-w-led

( driver – )

This toggles the state of the LED on the Raspberry Pi Pico W or Raspberry Pi Pico 2 W.

pico-w-cyw43-net-ipv6

This pico-w-cyw43-net-ipv6 class has the following class:

<pico-w-cyw43-net-ipv6>

The <pico-w-cyw43-net-ipv6> class inherits from the <simple-cyw43-net-ipv6> class, providing functionality specific to the Raspberry Pi Pico W.

It has the following constructor:

new

( sm-index pio-instance driver – )

This instantiates an instance with a PIO state machine sm-index, and a PIO instance (pio::PIO0 or pio::PIO1 or, on the RP2350, pio::PIO2) for the PIO program and state machine for implementing the half-duplex protocol for communicating with the CYW43xxx.

It has the following methods:

init-cyw43-net

( driver – )

This initializes a <pico-w-cyw43-net-ipv6> instance.

init-cyw43-net-no-handler

( driver – )

This initalizes a <pico-w-cyw43-net-ipv6> instance without starting an endpoint processing task.

pico-w-led!

( state driver – )

This sets the LED on the Raspberry Pi Pico W or Raspberry Pi Pico 2 W to state.

pico-w-led@

( driver – state )

This gets the state of the LED on the Raspberry Pi Pico W or Raspberry Pi Pico 2 W.

toggle-pico-w-led

( driver – )

This toggles the state of the LED on the Raspberry Pi Pico W or Raspberry Pi Pico 2 W.

net-misc

The net-misc module contains a number of internal and convenience words, notably:

make-ipv4-addr

( addr0 addr1 addr2 addr3 – addr )

Construct an IPv4 address, in the typical order, e.g.:

192 168 1 1 net-misc::make-ipv4-addr

make-ipv6-addr

( addr0 addr1 addr2 addr3 addr4 addr5 addr6 addr7 – ipv6-0 ipv6-1 ipv6-2 ipv6-3 )

Construct an IPv6 address from groups of 16 bits in the typical order, i.e. the highest significance groups of bits are lowest on the data stack, e.g.:

$FF02 0 0 0 0 0 2 1 net-misc::make-ipv6-addr

ipv4.

( addr – )

Print an IPv4 address formatted in the typical x.y.z.w format to the console.

ipv6.

( addr-0 addr-1 addr-2 addr-3 – )

Print an IPv6 address formatted in an uncompressed, uppercase hexadecimal format to the console.

PicoCalc words

zeptoforth has support for the PicoCalc, a device that provides a display, keyboard, speakers, and an SD card slot for boards that fit the pinout of a Raspberry Pi Pico 1 (including a Raspberry Pi Pico 1 W, Raspberry Pi Pico 2, Raspberry Pi Pico 2 W, Pimoroni Pico Plus 2, and Pimoroni Pico Plus 2 W). General directions as to the installation and use of zeptoforth on the PicoCalc are detailed in USING_THE_PICOCALC.md at the root of this directory tree. This file contains API documentation for the API exposed by the graphical and text-only PicoCalc terminal emulators.

Note that the core that the PicoCalc tasks run on defaults to core 1 of the RP2040 or RP2350, but can be manually set by defining a globally-visible constant in flash named select-picocalc-tasks-core prior to compiling PicoCalc support. This is useful if you are also installing zeptoIP on your PicoCalc, as zeptoIP runs very CPU-heavy tasks on core 1 which will significantly slow down the PicoCalc terminal emulator if it is also running on core 1.

picocalc-term

The picocalc-term module contains the following words:

term-console

( – )

Select the PicoCalc terminal emulator as the console for the current task. If the PicoCalc welcome message has not been displayed yet, display it on the PicoCalc screen. Also, set term-cols to the width of the PicoCalc terminal emulator in characters.

with-term-lock

( xt – )

Carry out an operation with the PicoCalc terminal locked. Note that executing operations that print to the PicoCalc terminal should be avoided because they may block indefinitely.

with-term-display

( xt – ) xt: ( display – )

Carry out an operation against the PicoCalc terminal’s display with the PicoCalc terminal locked. It is highly recommended that the user update the terminal’s display or graphics drawn to it may not be displayed. Note that executing operations that print to the PicoCalc terminal should be avoided because they may block indefinitely.

term-pixels-dim@

( – width height )

Get the terminal dimensions in pixels.

term-dim@

( – width height )

Get the terminal dimensions in characters.

term-char-dim@

( – width height )

Get the terminal character dimensions in pixels.

term-font@

( – font )

Get the terminal font.

read-battery

( – battery-level )

Read the battery level.

set-backlight

( desired-backlight-level – actual-backlight-level )

Set the backlight level.

read-backlight

( – backlight-level )

Read the backlight level.

set-kbd-backlight

( desired-kbd-backlight-level – actual-kbd-backlight-level )

Set the keyboard backlight level.

read-kbd-backlight

( – kbd-backlight-level )

Read the keyboard backlight level.

visual-bell-enabled!

( enabled – )

Set visual bell enabled. This defaults to false.

visual-bell-enabled@

( – enabled )

Get visual bell enabled. This defaults to false.

audible-bell-enabled!

( enabled – )

Set audible bell enabled. This defaults to false.

audible-bell-enabled@

( – enabled )

Get audible bell enabled. This defaults to false.

screenshot-hook!

( xt – )

Set the screenshot hook. This defaults to 0, indicating no hook set.

screenshot-hook@

( – xt )

Get the screenshot hook. This defaults to 0, indicating no hook set.

picocalc-sound

The picocalc-sound module contains the following words:

play-tone

( end-tick D: pitch – )

Generate a tone of pitch (an S31.32 value in Hz) ending at end-tick relative to systick::systick-counter, with ticks being 100 microsecond increments. Note that tones ending earlier override tones ending later, and a total of up to 8 tones are tracked at any one time.

play-tone-for-duration

( duration D: pitch – )

Generate a tone of pitch (an S31.32 value in Hz) of duration ticks, with ticks being 100 microsecond increments. Note that tones ending earlier override tones ending later, and a total of up to 8 tones are tracked at any one time.

beep

( – )

This is a convenience word to generate a 1245 Hz, i.e. D6#, tone for 125 milliseconds. This word is used internally to generate the audible bell.

picocalc-bios

The picocalc-bios module contains the following words:

emulate-keys?

( – flag )

This is a value that defaults to false that can be set to true to enable emulating key presses using the serial console as input. This is primarily of use for testing PicoCalc support without using an actual PicoCalc.

picocalc-screenshot

Compiling extra/rp_common/picocalc_screenshoto.fs makes the following words available in the picocalc-screenshot module:

screenshot-fs!

( fs – )

Set the FAT32 filesystem object for saving screenshots with Attention (Break (Shift-Escape) on the PicoCalc keyboard, Control-T on the serial and USB CDC consoles) s. This filesystem defaults to the SD card FAT32 filesystem first, if configured, or the PSRAM FAT32 filesystem second, if configured, or the on-board flash storage FAT32 filesystem third, if configured.

screenshot-fs@

( – fs )

Get the FAT32 filesystem object for saving screenshots with the attention key combo.

screenshot-path!

( path-addr path-bytes – )

Set the base path for saving screenshots with Attention (Break (Shift-Escape) on the PicoCalc keyboard, Control-T on the serial and USB CDC consoles) s. This path defaults to /SCREEN. Note that this directory will be automatically created if it does not exist when taking a screenshot with the console attention key combo, but its parent directorie(s) will not be automatically created.

screenshot-path@

( – path-addr path-bytes )

Get the base path for saving screenshots with the attention key combo.

take-screenshot

( path-addr path-bytes fs – )

This is the actual word that implements the taking of screenshots. Note that when this word is executed directly the display is not flashed unlike when taking a screenshot with the console attention key combo.

fat32-tools

Compiling extra/rp_common/picocalc_fat32.fs adds the following words to the fat32-tools module:

blocks-fs@

( – fs )

This returns the FAT32 filesystem object for the on-board flash ‘blocks’ FAT32 filesystem if extra/common/setup_blocks_fat32.fs has been compiled before extra/rp_common/picocalc_fat32.fs.

blocks-fs:

( – )

This sets the current FAT32 filesystem to the FAT32 filesystem object for the on-board flash ‘blocks’ FAT32 filesystem if extra/common/setup_blocks_fat32.fs has been compiled before extra/rp_common/picocalc_fat32.fs.

sd-fs@

( – fs )

This returns the FAT32 filesystem object for the FAT32 filesystem in partition 0 of the SDHC or SDXC card inserted in your PicoCalc unless the constant no-sd-fs was defined in flash prior to compiling extra/rp_common/picocalc_fat32.fs.

sd-fs:

( – )

This sets the current FAT32 filesystem to the FAT32 filesystem object for the FAT32 filesystem in partition 0 of the SDHC or SDXC card inserted in your PicoCalc unless the constant no-sd-fs was defined in flash prior to compiling extra/rp_common/picocalc_fat32.fs.

psram-fs@

( – fs )

This returns the FAT32 filesystem object for the FAT32 filesystem in PSRAM if extra/rp2350/setup_pico_plus_2_psram_fat32.fs was compiled before compiling extra/rp_common/picocalc_fat32.fs.

`psram-fs:

( – )

This sets the current FAT32 filesystem to the FAT32 filesystem object for the FAT32 filesystem in PSRAM if extra/rp2350/setup_pico_plus_2_psram_fat32.fs was compiled before compiling extra/rp_common/picocalc_fat32.fs.

SHA-256

There is currently a software implementation of SHA-256 for zeptoforth. This implementation does not take advantage of hardware SHA-256 accelerators, even though this is planned for future development.

Note that a basic limitation of SHA-256 is that the total data size must be smaller than 2^64 bits, i.e. 2^56 bytes. For most practical applications this should not be a problem.

The source code for the software implementation of SHA-256 is in extra/common/sha256.fs. This code is based closely off of https://github.com/amonsier/sha-2 which in turn is closely based off https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/SHA-2 .

There is a set of SHA-256 tests in test/common/sha256.fs.

sha-256

The sha-256 module contains the following words:

size-of-sha-256-hash

( – bytes )

Size of an SHA-256 hash in bytes

sha-256-size

( – bytes )

Size of SHA-256 structure in bytes

init-sha-256

( hash sha-256 – )

Initialize an SHA-256 streaming calculation.

hash: address of hash array, where the result is delivered

sha-256: address of an SHA-256 structure

If all the data you are calculating the hash value on is not available in a contiguous buffer in memory, this is where you should start. Instantiate a SHA-256 structure, and invoke this word. Once a SHA-256 hash has been calculated the SHA-256 structure can be initialized again for the next calculation.

write-sha-256

( data len sha-256 – )

Stream more input for an on-going SHA-256 calculation.

data: address of data to be added to the calculation

len: length of the data to add, in bytes

sha-256: address of a previously initialized SHA-256 structure

This word may be invoked an arbitrary number of times between initialization and closing, but the data length is limited by the SHA-256 algorithm: the total number of bits (i.e. the total number of bytes times eight) must be representable by a 64-bit unsigned integer. While that is not a practical limitation, the result is unpredictable if that limit is exceeded.

This word may be invoked on empty data (zero length), although that obviously will not add any data.

close-sha-256

( sha-256 – )

Conclude an SHA-256 streaming calculation, making the hash value available.

sha-256: address of a previously initialized SHA-256 structure

After this word has been invoked, the result is available in the hash buffer that initially was provided. The address of the hash value is returned for convenience, but you should feel free to drop it; it is simply the address of the first byte of your initially provided hash array.

Invoking this word for a calculation with no data (the writing function has never been invoked, or it only has been invoked with empty data) is legal. It will calculate the SHA-256 value of the empty string.

calc-sha-256

( input len hash – )

The simple SHA-256 calculation word

input: address of the data the hash will be calculated on

len: length of the input data, in bytes

hash: address of hash array, where the result is delivered

If all the data you are calculating the hash value on is available in a contiguous buffer in memory, this is the word you should use.

The length must be correspond to an unsigned 64-bit number of bits (i.e. the length times eight must be less than 2^64).

Text Displays

In addition to bitmap and pixmap framebuffer-based graphics, there is also optional support for pure text displays with character matrices along with inverted video character maps. Currently support exists for SSD1306, ST7735S, and SH1122-based displays with monospace bitmap fonts.

Support for SSD1306-based text displays is in extra/common/ssd1306_text.fs. With SSD1306-based displays the user can select contrast settings from 0 to 255.

Support for ST7735S-based text displays is in extra/common/st7735s_text.fs. With ST7735S-based displays the user can select 16-bit (5-bit red, 6-bit green, and 5-bit blue) foreground and background colors and backlight on/off.

Support for SH1122-based text displays is in extra/common/sh1122_text.fs. With SH1122-based displays the user can select contrast settings from 0 to 255 and foreground and background grayscale values from 0 to 15.

Note that these require extra/common/clip.fs, extra/common/bitmap.fs, extra/common/font.fs, and extra/common/text_display.fs to be loaded.

text-display

The text-display module contains the following standalone words:

text-buf-size

( cols rows char-cols char-rows – bytes )

This word calculates a buffer size for a text display’s text buffer with cols columns and rows rows in display pixel dimensions and char-cols columns and char-rows rows in font pixel dimensions.

invert-buf-size

( cols rows char-cols char-rows – bytes )

This word calculates a buffer size for a text display’s inverted video buffer with cols columns and rows rows in display pixel dimensions and char-cols columns and char-rows rows in font pixel dimensions.

The text-display module contains the following class:

<text-display>

This class has the following constructor:

new

( text-buffer-addr invert-buffer-addr font cols rows self – )

This constructs a text display with a text buffer text-buffer-addr with a size calculated with text-buf-size, an inverted video buffer invert-buffer-addr with a size calculated with invert-buf-size, a font font, and cols columns and rows rows in display pixel dimensions.

This class has the following methods:

clear-display

( self – )

This clears a display and dirties it.

set-dirty

( self – )

This dirties an entire display.

dirty-char

( col row self – )

This dirties a character at column col and row row.

dirty?

( self – dirty? )

This gets whether a display is dirty.

dirty-rect@

( self – start-col start-row end-col end-row )

This gets a display’s dirty rectangle. If the display is not dirty, start-col will equal end-col and start-row will equal end-row.

clear-dirty

( self – )

This clears a display’s dirty state.

dim@

( self – cols rows )

This gets a display’s dimensions in characters.

char!

( c col row self – )

This sets column col and row row of the display to character c, dirtying the display.

char@

( col row self – c )

This gets the character at column col and row row of the display.

string!

( c-addr u col row self – )

This sets a horizontal line of characters starting from column col on the left at row row to the string represented by the address c-addr and count u.

invert!

( invert? col row self – )

This sets the inverted video state of column col and row row to invert?.

toggle-invert!

( col row self – )

This toggles the inverted video state of column col and row row.

invert@

( col row self – invert? )

This gets the inverted video state of column col and row row.

pixel@

( pixel-col pixel-row self – pixel-set? )

This gets the pixel value of a pixel at pixel column pixel-col and pixel row pixel-row.

ssd1306-text

This module contains the following class:

<ssd1306-text>

This class has the following constructor:

new

( pin0 pin1 text-buffer-addr invert-buffer-addr font columns rows i2c-addr i2c-device ssd1306 – )

This constructor initializes an I2C SSD1306 display with the SDA and SCK pins specified as GPIO pins pin0 and pin1 (it does not matter which is which), a text backing buffer at text-buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <text-display> instances), an inverted video backing buffer at invert-buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <text-display> instances), columns columns, rows rows, the I2C address i2c-addr, the I2C device index i2c-device (note that this must match the I2C device index for pins pin0 and pin1), and the <ssd1306-text> instance being initialized, ssd1306.

This class has the following methods:

update-display

( ssd1306 – )

This updates the SSD1306-based display with the current contents of its dirty rectangle, and then clears its dirty state. This must be called to update the display’s contents after drawing to the display, which otherwise has no effect on the display itself.

display-contrast!

( constrast ssd1306 – )

This sets the contrast of an SSD1306-based display to a value from 0 to 255.

st7735s-text

The st7735s-text module contains the following words:

rgb16

( r g b – color )

Create a 16-bit color with 5 bits for red, 6 bits for green, and 5 bits for blue from a red/green/blue triplet of values from 0 to 255 each.

<st7735s-text>

( – class )

The <st7735s-text> class is the class for 16-bit SPI ST7735S-based displays with 5-bit red, 6-bit green, 5-bit blue foreground and background colors and bitmap backing buffers. It inherits from the <bitmap> class and can be drawn to using the operations defined in that class. It maintains a dirty rectangle, which is updated when the user invokes its update-display method. Note that column zero is on the lefthand side of the display and row zero is on the top of the display.

The <st7735s-text> class includes the following constructor:

new

( fg-color bg-color din-pin clk-pin dc-pin cs-pin backlight-pin reset-pin text-buffer-addr invert-buffer-addr font columns rows spi-device st7735s – )

This constructor initializes an SPI ST7735S display at the SPI device spi-device, a text backing buffer at text-buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <text-display> instances), an inverted video backing buffer at invert-buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <text-display> instances), columns columns, rows rows, the DIN pin din-pin, the CLK pin clk-pin, the DC pin dc-pin, the chip-select pin cs-pin, the backlight pin backlight-pin, the reset pin reset-pin, a 16-bit foreground color fg-color, a 16-bit background color bg-color, and the <st7735s> instance being initialized, st7735s. Note that din-pin and clk-pin must match the SPI device spi-device specified.

The <st7735s> class includes the following method:

update-display

( st7735s – )

This updates the ST7735S-based display with the current contents of its dirty rectangle, and then clears its dirty state. This must be called to update the display’s contents after drawing to the display, which otherwise has no effect on the display itself.

backlight!

( backlight st7735s – )

Set the on/off state of the ST7735S-based display’s backlight.

fg-color!

( fg-color st7735s – )

Set the foreground color of the ST7735S-based display and dirty the display.

bg-color!

( bg-color st7735s – )

Set the background color of the ST7735S-based display and dirty the display.

fg-color@

( st7735s – fg-color )

Get the foreground color of the ST7735S-based display.

bg-color@

( st7735s – bg-color )

Get the background color of the ST7735S-based display.

sh1122-text

The sh1122-text module contains the following words:

<sh1122-text>

( – class )

The <sh1122-text> class is the class for grayscale SPI SH1122-based displays with 4-bit foreground and background gray levels and bitmap backing buffers. It inherits from the <bitmap> class and can be drawn to using the operations defined in that class. It maintains a dirty rectangle, which is updated when the user invokes its update-display method. Note that column zero is on the lefthand side of the display and row zero is on the top of the display.

The <sh1122-text> class includes the following constructor:

new

( fg-gray bg-gray din-pin clk-pin dc-pin cs-pin reset-pin text-buffer-addr invert-buffer-addr font columns rows spi-device sh1122 – )

This constructor initializes an SPI SH1122 display at the SPI device spi-device, a text backing buffer at text-buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <text-display> instances), an inverted video backing buffer at invert-buffer-addr (with the same considerations as backing buffers for other <text-display> instances), columns columns, rows rows, the DIN pin din-pin, the CLK pin clk-pin, the DC pin dc-pin, the chip-select pin cs-pin, the reset pin reset-pin, a 4-bit foreground gray level fg-gray, a 4-bit background gray level bg-gray, and the <sh1122> instance being initialized, sh1122. Note that din-pin and clk-pin must match the SPI device spi-device specified.

The <sh1122> class includes the following method:

update-display

( sh1122 – )

This updates the SH1122-based display with the current contents of its dirty rectangle, and then clears its dirty state. This must be called to update the display’s contents after drawing to the display, which otherwise has no effect on the display itself.

display-contrast!

( constrast sh1122 – )

This sets the contrast of an SH1122-based display to a value from 0 to 255.

fg-gray!

( fg-gray sh1122 – )

Set the foreground gray of the SH1122-based display and dirty the display.

bg-gray!

( bg-gray sh1122 – )

Set the background gray of the SH1122-based display and dirty the display.

fg-gray@

( sh1122 – fg-gray )

Get the foreground gray of the SH1122-based display.

bg-gray@

( sh1122 – bg-gray )

Get the background gray of the SH1122-based display.

Turtle graphics

Optional support for turtle graphics is in extra/rp2040/turtle.fs. It is designed for compatibility with Thurtle, which is based on WAForth and runs in web browsers, and Forthtoise, which is on top of gforth and uses SDL. It allows changing the color of both the lines drawn and the turtle, but does not currently support changing the line thickness (even though that will likely change in the near future).

It is currently setup up for use with 16-bit graphics on the 160x80 ST7735S-based display on the Waveshare RP2040-LCD-0.96 but can be readily modified for other ST7735S-based displays, including ones on non-RP2040 based boards. Porting to SSD1306-based displays should be trivial and is an exercise left to the user.

The display the turtle is in is such that the (0, 0) lies in the center of the display (all distances are specified in pixels, and x coordinates increase from left to right while y coordinates increase from bottom to top) and a heading of 0 degrees (all angles here are specified in degrees, not radians) is pointing directly up along the Y dimension. The turtle starts (and is reset to by home) at (0, 0) with a heading of 0 degrees. Also note that the turtle begins pen down, the turtle starts out with the color (0, 255, 0), i.e. green, and the lined drawn by the turtle starts out with the color (255, 255, 255), i.e white. Note however that not all possibly-specified colors can be distinguished due to the 16-bit color of the display.

turtle

The turtle module contains the following words:

setpencolor

( r g b – )

Set the current pen color, where r, g, and b are values between 0 to 255 (but note that 16-bit displays do not permit all possible colors in this color space to be distinguished from one another).

setturtlecolor

( r g b – )

Set the current turtle color, where r, g, and b are values between 0 and 255 (likewise not all colors so specified may be distinguished in 16-bit color).

forward

( pixels – )

Move the turtle forward a given number of pixels.

backward

( pixel – )

Move the turtle backward a given number of pixels.

left

( angle – )

Turn the turtle left angle degrees (not radians).

right

( right – )

Turn the turtle right angle degrees (not radians).

penup

( – )

Pen up, i.e. stop drawing lines with turtle movement.

pendown

( – )

Pen down, i.e. start drawing lines with turtle movement.

getpendown

( – pen-down? )

Get whether the pen is down.

setxy

( x y – )

Set the position of the turtle to x and y, where (0, 0) is in the center of the display. The x coordinate increases from left to right, and the y coordinate increases from bottom to top. Note that if the pen is down a line will be drawn.

getxy

( – x y )

Get the position of the turtle, where (0, 0) is in the center of the display. The x coordinate increases from left to right, and the y coordinate increases from bottom to top. Note that the reported coordinate is in pixels, so precision may be lost.

setheading

( angle – )

Set the heading of the turtnle to angle degrees, where 0 is pointing up along the Y dimension and 90 is pointing left along the X dimension.

hideturtle

( – )

Hide the turtle.

showturtle

( – )

Show the turtle.

getshowturtle

( – show-turtle? )

Get whether the turtle is shown.

updateoff

( – )

Disable updating the display.

updateon

( – )

Enable updating the display, and update it.

getupdateon

( – update-on? )

Get whether updating the display is on.

clear

( – )

Clear the display but leave the turtle in the same position and heading (and it will remain visible unless the turtle is hidden).

setpensize

( pixels – )

Set the pen size in pixels.

getpensize

( – pixels )

Get the pen size in pixels.

home

( – )

Move the turtle to the center of the display, pointing up. No lines are drawn by this.

zeptoed

zeptoed is an optional text editor that may be loaded into RAM or compiled to flash for the purpose of editing files in FAT32 filesystems. It supports editing in multiple buffers simultaneously, copy/cut-and-paste operations, undo operations, LF/CRLF conversion, Unicode (UTF-8), and indentation and unindentation operations. It requires a fully functional ANSI terminal, and hence cannot be used under zeptocom.js.

Each buffer takes up the middle portion of the screen, i.e. excluding the top and bottom lines of the screen. The top line is taken up by the path of the file corresponding to the current buffer and, if the current buffer is dirty (i.e. a modification has been made to it since has time it has been written out or reverted), an asterisk indicating the fact. The bottom line is taken up by the “minibuffer”, which displays messages and takes prompted user input.

Note that zeptoed requires a FAT32 filesystem to be registered via fat32-tools::current-fs! or fat32-tools::init-simple-fat32. In most cases the latter will be the easiest approach (e.g. one is using SDHC/SDXC cards containing only one partition and one is using only one FAT32 filesystem).

zeptoed lives in extra/common/zeptoed.fs and is dependent upon extra/common/dyn_buffer.fs. Both can be loaded at once by loading extra/common/zeptoed_all.fs with utils/codeload3.sh, zeptocom.js, or e4thcom.

Words

zeptoed

( path-addr path-bytes – )

Open the file at the path specified by path-addr path-bytes in the current FAT32 filesystem into a new buffer in zeptoed.

zed

( path-addr path-bytes – )

The same as zeptoed in case you feel like zeptoed is too long to enter.

zeptoed-heap-size

( – bytes )

This a value containing the base heap size used by zeptoed while it is running. It defaults to 65536 bytes. Note that zeptoed actually uses more space for data than this, because this does not include the heap bitmap or arena-allocated structures used by zeptoed.

zeptoed-indent-size

( – spaces )

This is a value containing the number of spaces taken up by a single indentation. It defaults to 2 spaces.

zeptoed-tab-size

( – spaces )

This is a value containing the number of spaces that a tab character is aligned to. It defaults to 8 spaces.

zeptoed-save-crlf-enabled

( – enabled? )

This is a value containing whether files saved by zeptoed will use CRLF endlines (rather than the default of LF endlines). It defaults to false.

Key mappings

zeptoed has the following key mappings; all other non-control characters will be inserted at the cursor:

Enter: Insert a newline with indentation to match the indentation of the preceding line.

Tab: Indent the current line or the current selection by one indentation incremnt.

Shift-Tab: Unindent the current lien or the current selection by one indentation increment. Note that tabs may be automatically converted to spaces in the process.

Control-Meta-Tab: Insert a single tab character (rather than indent).

Backspace: If there is no selection, delete backward (left) one character; if there is a selection, delete the current selection.

Delete: If there is no selection, delete forward (right) one character; if there is a selection, delete the current selection.

Left, Control-B: Move the cursor backward (left) one character.

Right, Control-F: Move the cursor forward (right) one character.

Up: Move the cursor up by one row.

Down: Move the cursor down by one row.

Page Up: Move the cursor up by roughly one screen.

Page Down: Move the cursor down by roughly one screen.

Home: Move the cursor to the start of the document.

End: Move the cursor to the nd of the document.

Control-Space: Toggle selection; if there previously was no selection, the selection point is set to the current position of the cursor.

Control-A: Move the cursor to the start of the line; note that under many terminal programs (GNU Screen, picocom) Control-A is captured, and generating a Control-A requires more keys to be entered (e.g. entering Control-A again under picocom).

Control-E: Move the cursor to the end of the line.

Control-N: Go to the next buffer.

Control-P: Go to the previous buffer.

Control-O: Open a buffer with the specified file path; if a file with that path exists it is loaded, otherwise it is created.

Control-V: Exit; note that if dirty buffers exist, the user will be prompted whether they wish to exit.

Control-W: Write the current buffer to its file and mark it clean.

Control-Meta-W: Select another file and write the current buffer into it, creating it if it did not exist and overwriting its contents if it did, and set the current buffer to point to it; the current buffer will be marked as clean.

Control-X: Reload the current buffer from its file and mark it clean.

Control-Meta-X: Close the current buffer; note that if the current buffer is dirty, the user will be prompted whether they wish to close it.

Control-K: Cut the current selection and transfer it to the clipboard.

Control-Meta-K: Copy the current selection and transfer it to the clipboard.

Control-Y: Paste the contents of the clipboard at the cursor.

Control-Z: Carry out one undo; note that some operations have their undos combined, while others may be split into multiple undos (i.e. are non-atomic).

Control-L: Refresh the display, e.g. if the terminal has changed size.